Guide to the Center for the Humanities Records 1974-2012
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
Center for the Humanities Records
1974-2012
1975-2000
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center Special Collections & Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu
RG 221
Oregon State University. Center for the Humanities.
7.8 cubic feet, including 31 photographs and 1 audiocassette 8 boxes
The Center for the Humanities Records document the formation, functioning and activities of both the Oregon State University Center for the Humanities as well as the Humanities Development Program that preceded it. In addition to daily operations and major events supported by the Center, the collection also details the academic certificate programs administered by the Center as well as the resident fellows that it hosted. The records likewise provide a thorough accounting of the International Film Series, which the Center sponsored for over twenty years. The Humanities Development Program was formed in 1977 and succeded by the Center for the Humanities in 1984. Both the program and the Center were run by OSU English professor Peter Copek until his death in 2001.
Historical Note:
The pre-history of Oregon State University's Center for the Humanities can be traced to the Humanities Grant Study Committee, a collection of fifteen department chairs and faculty representatives from OSU's departments of Art, English, History, Modern Languages, Music, Philosophy, and Religious Studies, as well as the College of Liberal Arts Dean's Office. Led by faculty members Gordon Gilkey and Richard Astro, the study committee was charged with evaluating the feasibility of major changes to the humanities curriculum at Oregon State and exploring the possibility of applying for funds from the National Endowment for the Humanities that might facilitate changes of this sort.
The product of this group's work was a successful NEH Development Grant proposal that made a significant impact on the university's intellectual culture. The 1977 grant, titled "An Exploration of Community," steered just under $1,000,000 in federal money to the university for use in developing curricula in four areas: Northwest Studies; Marine and Maritime Studies; Community Studies; and Studies in Science, Technology, and Values. Administered by the newly created Humanities Development Program, these interdisciplinary certificate programs were meant to both broadly strengthen OSU's humanities offerings and to link study in the humanities to courses already extant in the university's science and professional schools.
The Humanities Development Program was run from the outset by Peter Copek, a faculty member in English, and it succeeded in filling a void at OSU. During the program's six year lifespan, over fifty faculty members participated in the development effort, creating sixty-five courses in what became three program areas. (The program's "Community Studies" and "Science, Technology and Values" offerings were reorganized as "Twentieth Century Studies.")
The Humanities Development Program contributed to the vigor of campus life in other ways, in part through its use of NEH funds and other support from organizations including the Oregon Humanities Committee to sponsor a wide array of campus events. Seminars, musical performances and film screenings were common sources of outreach for the program, which also supported and helped to organize at least four conferences. Perhaps most notably, Copek, who maintained a scholarly interest in film studies, co-founded the International Film Series, which screened independent and foreign films every weekend during the academic year for over twenty years, beginning in 1977.
The OSU Center for the Humanities was created as a result of a second NEH grant, this time a challenge grant which, in 1984, awarded $700,000 to the university following its own success in raising an additional $1.4 million from private donors. The $2.1 million total was used to endow the Center which, as with the Humanities Development Program before, was run by Peter Copek. In addition to continued offerings within the certificate programs, the new center also unveiled a fellowship program which provided stipends for both OSU faculty and "external fellows" to conduct research in the humanities, usually for one term. For external fellows, the funds provided by the Center supported travel, lodging and office space. Similarly, the Center lessened the load on internal OSU fellows by paying others to teach the courses to which they were normally assigned. The Center likewise continued to organize and support various events on campus, including multiple music festivals, a lecture series (keynoted by Gore Vidal) marking the bicentennial of the U.S. Constitution, and a symposium on the military-industrial complex.
In its early years, Center for the Humanities operations were run out of an office located in Moreland Hall. That changed in June 1989 when the Center moved into what would become its permanent home, a former sorority house on Jefferson Avenue. At the time of its formal purchase by the university in 1993, the facility was christened the Autzen House in honor of the Autzen Foundation of Portland, which provided major funding for the acquisition of the space.
The Center enjoyed stability and moderate growth throughout the 1990s, but change came suddenly in June 2001, when Peter Copek died at the age of fifty-six from a heart attack that struck in the aftermath of gall bladder surgery. English professor David Robinson was subsequently named director of the Center. Under Robinson's leadership, the OSU Center for the Humanities has continued to sponsor academic fellowships and to support campus and community offerings, including two annual events - The Magic Barrel Reading to Fight Hunger and The OSU Holocaust Memorial Program. The certificate programs that emerged from the original 1977 NEH grant are no longer offered at OSU; removal of the last of them, Twentieth Century Studies, was initiated in 2005.
The Center for the Humanities Records document the creation and activities of the Center itself, and also tell the story of the entity that preceded the Center at Oregon State University, the Humanities Development Program.
The collection includes, in Series I, records describing the formation, operation and assessment of the Humanities Development Program, which was first conceptualized in 1975 and came into being following OSU's receipt of a National Endowment for the Humanities grant in 1977. Events sponsored or co-sponsored by the program, including lecture series, film screenings and stage performances, have been arranged into Series II. The primary thrust of the NEH grant that funded the Humanities Development Program was the creation of four interdisciplinary study certificate programs - two in Community Studies, one in Northwest Studies and another in Marine and Maritime Studies - and records relating to these initiatives are available in Series III.
Series IV is devoted to the second NEH grant, a challenge grant funded in 1984, that led to the creation and endowment of the OSU Center for the Humanities. The Center's operations are described in Series V and include records of the Center's Program Advisory Board, Center newsletters, annual reports, materials relating to budget and facilities, newspaper clippings and a small collection of photographs. The Center's correspondence - mostly written by Peter Copek - with a wide array of individuals and organizations is available in Series VI. Series VII focuses on events sponsored or co-sponsored by the Center, including music festivals, colloquia and a high-profile lecture series celebrating the bicentennial of the U.S. Constitution in 1987. The successful proposals and subsequent tenures of various Center fellows, both internal and external, have been arranged into Series VIII. Finally, Series IX lends detailed insight into the International Film Series, a Center-supported initiative which brought foreign and independent cinema to the OSU campus every weekend during the term for more than twenty years.
The Center for the Humanities Records are arranged into nine series: I. Humanities Development Program - Formation and Operations, 1975-1984; II. Humanities Development Program - Events, 1975-1983; III. Certificate Programs, 1975-1999; IV. National Endowment for the Humanities Challenge Grant, 1982-1989; V. Center for the Humanities - Operations, 1983-2012; VI. Center for the Humanities - Correspondence, 1974-2000; VII. Center for the Humanities - Events, 1985-2000; VIII. Center for the Humanities - Fellows, 1987-2000; IX. International Film Series, 1977-1999.
The Peter Copek Papers (MSS Copek) document the life, work and academic connections of Peter Copek, who served as director of the Humanities Development Program and of the OSU Center for the Humanities for the better part of twenty-four years. The Special Collections & Archives Research Center (SCARC) also holds the papers of Paul Lawrence Farber (MSS Farber), who was Acting Director of the Humanities Development Program in 1984, while the program was being transformed into a full-fledged center. Materials related to the Center for the Humanities are likewise held in the Oregon State University Memorabilia Collection (MC), the President's Office Records of John V. Byrne (RG 13 SG 15), the Academic Affairs Records (RG 22), and the Research Office Records (RG 170).
OSU President Emeritus John Byrne shared his memories of the creation of the Center for the Humanities and the purchase of a permanent facility for the Center in an oral history interview held in the OSU Sesquicentennial Oral History Collection (OH 26). That facility, now known as Autzen House, was originally Gamma Phi Beta sorority, an organization that is also documented by a SCARC photograph collection (P 277).
Collection is open for research.
The majority of the records described in this collection were transferred to the University Archives in 2001 by the Oregon State University Center for the Humanities. In 2015, two cubic feet of materials were transferred into RG 221 from the Peter Copek Papers (MSS Copek). That same year, the contents of two publications were also transferred into the collection: Humanities Development Program publications (PUB 231) and Center for the Humanities Newsletter and Criterion (PUB 281).
Astro, Richard.; Copek, Peter J., 1945-; Robinson, David, 1947-
Oregon State University. College of Liberal Arts.; Oregon State University. Humanities Development Program.; National Endowment for the Humanities.
Film series.; Humanities--Study and teaching (Higher)--Oregon.; Humanities--United States.
Audiocassettes.; Photographic prints.
Colleges and Universities; Corvallis; Literature; Oregon; Performing Arts; Photographs; Sound Recordings
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Humanities Development Program - Formation and Operations, 1975-1984; Series I
  Documentation of the original idea for the Humanities Development Program, as well as the NEH grant ("An Exploration of Community") that made it a reality, can be found in Series I. The series also contains materials reflecting the program's daily activities, two sets of reports assessing the workings of the program, and content generated by the task force charged with transitioning the program into a full-fledged center.
  - "Innovation in the Humanities at OSU: A Report." Prepared by the Humanities Grant Study Committee, College of Liberal Arts, July 1975 (Box 1)
  - "Consultants Program Grant Proposal." Submitted to the National Endowment for the Humanities Division of Education Programs by Oregon State University, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - "An Exploration of Community." Development Grant Proposal submitted to the National Endowment for the Humanities by Oregon State University, April 1976; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program Assessment Reports, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    File includes annual reports for 1976-1977 and 1977-1978; "The Rosenheim Report," an independent review of the program conducted by Robert Albrecht, Walter Jones and Edward Rosenheim; curricula vitae for program administrators Peter Copek and Bill Robbins; program budget expenditures and projections; and student evaluations of courses sponsored by the program.
  - "The Moss Report." Evaluation of the OSU Humanities Development Program by a NEH site visit team led by H.G. Moss, 1979 (Box 1)
    File includes internal correspondence related to the report as well as a typescript: "Response to the Evaluation Report of the Oregon State University Humanities Development Program by the NEH Site Visit Team, February 1979," written by Peter Copek, June 1979.
  - Humanities Development Program - faculty research awards, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program operations, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program - newsletters and pamphlets, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program operations, 1980 (Box 1)
  - "A Proposal for a Matching Formula Title XII University Strengthening Grant." Submitted to the Board for International Food and Agricultural Development by Oregon State University, December 1980 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program operations, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program operations, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program operations, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Center for the Humanities Task Force, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program operations, 1984 (Box 1)
- Humanities Development Program - Events, 1975-1983; Series II
  The Humanities Development Program's public outreach agenda has been arranged into Series II. Major events sponsored or co-sponsored by the program have been itemized individually; calendars and flyers that provide a more thorough view of all of the program's engagement with the public are available as well.
  - "Literature and the Sea: A Course and Conference." Sea Grant project proposal submitted by Richard Astro, Anne Taylor and James McCauley, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - "Technology and Ocean Space." Conference held at the OSU Marine Science Center, 1978; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Files include materials concerning the conference budget, program and participants, as well as correspondence documenting its organization.
  - Humanities Development Program - Events Calendars, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - "Behind the Scenes," Northwest Film Series, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Development Program - Events Flyers, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - "Books and Critics: The Contemporary Reader." Colloquia and Lecture Series co-sponsored by the OSU Humanities Development Program, 1980 (Box 1)
  - "Middle East Film Week", 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - "University Seminars in Criticism," co-sponsored by the OSU Humanities Development Program, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - "Human Rights in Crisis: Latin America." Teach-In co-sponsored by the OSU Humanities Development Program, February 18, 1981 (Box 1)
  - "Keywords for the 80's." Conference co-sponsored by the OSU Humanities Development Program, April 27, 1981 (Box 1)
  - "Regionalism in Myth and Reality: A Pacific Northwest Symposium." Sponsored by the OSU Humanities Development Program, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    Files includes materials concerning the conference budget, program and participants, as well as correspondence documenting its organization.
  - "Hibakusha: Stories from Hiroshima." Political drama performed by the Modern Times Theater, sponsored by the OSU Humanities Development Program, 1982 (Box 1)
  - "The Golden Voice of the Great Southwest." Concert performance by Utah Phillips and Faith Petric, sponsored by the OSU Humanities Development Program, 1982 (Box 1)
- Certificate Programs, 1975-1999; Series III
  Items tracing the creation, evolution and operations of the Humanities Development Program's academic certificate programs have been arranged into Series III. The 1977 grant that led to the implementation of the Humanities Development Program specified that four interdisciplinary certificate programs be added to OSU's humanities offerings. Two of these programs - "Community as People, Place and Idea" and "Science, Technology and Community" - were later merged together under the umbrella of Twentieth Century Studies.
  - Community Studies Program course descriptions - Community as People, Place and Idea, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Community Studies Program course descriptions - Science, Technology and Community, 1979-1985 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1977 (Box 2)
  - "Humanities Marine Education Information Clearinghouse and Consultancy Program." Grant proposal submitted to the Office of Sea Grant, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, by Richard Astro, Robin Valencic and Dirk Frankenberg, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Meeting of the Humanities Marine Education Consortium, 1977 (Box 2)
    File includes materials concerning the meeting budget, program and participants, as well as correspondence documenting its organization.
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program course descriptions, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program operations, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Marine and Maritime Studies Program catalogs and flyers, undated (Box 2)
    File includes a catalog of the OSU Marine and Maritime Studies Slide Collection.
  - "Final Report on Northwest Studies Project at Oregon State University, 1975-1976." Submitted to the Director of Education Programs, National Endowment for the Humanities, by Robert Frank, November 1976 (Box 2)
  - Northwest Studies Program course descriptions, 1976-1980 (Box 2)
  - Northwest Studies Program courses poster, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Northwest Studies Program operations, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program operations, 1997-1999 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program course catalogs, 1988-1997 (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program brochures, undated (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Studies Program blank certificates and form letters, undated (Box 2)
  - Certificate Programs operations, 1981-1987 (Box 2)
  - Certificate Programs course catalogs, 1978-1988 (Box 2)
  - "Oregon State University Humanities Development Program Bibliography," Third Edition, August 1980 (Box 2)
    Bibliography of resources relevant to the program's course offerings in Northwest Studies; Marine and Maritime Studies; Community Studies; and Science, Technology and Values.
  - "Oregon State University Humanities Development Program Bibliography," Fifth Edition, September-November, 1982 (Box 2)
- National Endowment for the Humanities Challenge Grant, 1982-1989; Series IV
  Series IV holds materials documenting the work required to write, fulfill and implement the 1984 NEH Challenge Grant that led to the creation of the OSU Center for the Humanities. The series likewise includes several different iterations of the NEH grant proposal, which was finally submitted in May 1984.
  - NEH Challenge Grant preparation, 1982 (Box 3)
  - NEH Challenge Grant preparation, 1983 (Box 3)
  - "A Center for the Humanities, Oregon State University." Proposal submitted to the National Endowment for the Humanities, Division of Challenge Grants. By the Oregon State University Humanities Development Program, Peter J. Copek, Director, May 1, 1984 (Box 3)
  - NEH Challenge Grant preparation and administration, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases re: NEH Challenge Grant, 1984 (Box 3)
  - NEH Challenge Grant administration, 1985-1989 (Box 3)
- Center for the Humanities - Operations, 1983-2012; Series V
  Documentation of both the Center's on-going planning processes and regular operations is held in Series V. Of particular note are records pertaining to the Center's Program Advisory Committee, a group of OSU faculty, mostly from the College of Liberal Arts, who served two-year terms and who provided input on a number of issues related to the Center, including selection of both internal and external fellows. The series also holds materials related to the Center's budget and facilities, as well as annual reports, newsletters and newspaper clippings that provide detailed insight into the Center's activities over time. Where appropriate, date ranges reflect activities conducted over the course of a given academic year.
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Themes, 1984 (Box 3)
    This committee was charged with discussing potential areas of focus that the Center could consider for coordination and support during its first few years of operation.
  - Administrative Structure Proposal, 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Mission Statement and Long-Range Planning, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    The Center's Program Advisory Board consisted of OSU faculty, mostly from the College of Liberal Arts and usually serving for terms lasting two years. The board was charged with advising on most aspects of the Center's operations, including topical themes of support, selection of internal and external fellows, public programming, administration of grant funds, other fundraising, and issues related to Center facilities.
  - Program Advisory Board, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Program Advisory Board, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1985-1988 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports - Working Copies, 1993-1997 (Box 3)
  - "The Center for the Humanities - An Overview", 1994 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1996-2000 (Box 3)
  - Review of the Center for the Humanities, April 1994 (Box 3)
  - Center Fellows Publications Bibliography, December 1996 (Box 3)
  - Center for the Humanities Newsletter, 1987-1995 (Box 4)
  - Center for the Humanities Newsletter, 1996-2012 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Budget, 1988 (Box 4)